Cultural evolution is a dangerous child
التطور الحضاري هو بمثابة طفل خطر
for any species to let loose on its planet.
لأي جنس بما قد يجعله يخسر محيطه
By the time you realize what's happening, the child is a toddler,
في الوقت الذي تبدأ بتمييز ما يحدث، يكون هذا التطور طفلا صغيرا
up and causing havoc, and it's too late to put it back.
ولكنه يكبر ويسبب خرابا، ويصبح متأخرا أن تعيده إلى وضعه الأصلي
We humans are Earth's Pandoran species.
نحن البشر جنس الأرض البندوري - البندورا : صدوق الشرور -
We're the ones who let the second replicator out of its box,
نحن الذين أخرجنا المكرر أو (معيد التخليق) خارج صندوقه
and we can't push it back in.
ولا نستطيع إعادته مرة أخرى
We're seeing the consequences all around us.
نرى العواقب حولنا
Now that, I suggest, is the view that
والآن، كما أقترح، هو الرأي القائل
comes out of taking memetics seriously.
نحمل علم الميم محمل الجد (الميم: الوحدات الثقافية المنتقلة باللفظ أو الأعمال المتكرره)
And it gives us a new way of thinking about
ويعطينا طريقة جديدة في التفكير حوله
not only what's going on on our planet,
ليس فقط مايجري في كوكبنا
but what might be going on elsewhere in the cosmos.
بل ما يمكن ان يجري في أي مكان في الكون
So first of all, I'd like to say something about memetics
أولا أود أن أقول شيئاً عن علم الميم
and the theory of memes,
ونظرية الميم
and secondly, how this might answer questions about who's out there,
وثانياً، كيف يمكن أن يجيب هذا على أسئلة من هناك
if indeed anyone is.
إذا كان هناك أي أحد
So, memetics:
أذن علم الميم
memetics is founded on the principle of Universal Darwinism.
تأسس علم الميم على مبدأ الدارونية العالمية
Darwin had this amazing idea.
كان لدى داروين فكرة مدهشة
Indeed, some people say
في الحقيقة، بعض الأشخاص يقولون
it's the best idea anybody ever had.
إنها أفضل فكرة حملها أي شخص
Isn't that a wonderful thought, that there could be such a thing
أليست فكرة رائعة أن يكون شيئاً من هذا القبيل
as a best idea anybody ever had?
كأفضل فكرة حملها شخص ما؟
Do you think there could?
هل تعتقدون أنه من الممكن؟
Audience: No.
الجمهور: لا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Susan Blackmore: Someone says no, very loudly, from over there.
سوزان بلاكمور: أحد ما قال لا، بكل وضوح من هذه الناحية
Well, I say yes, and if there is, I give the prize to Darwin.
حسناً، أنا أقول نعم، وإن كان هناك، أنا أعطي الجائزة لداروين
Why?
لماذا؟
Because the idea was so simple,
لأن الفكرة كانت بسيطة جدا
and yet it explains all design in the universe.
وعلى ذلك فسر كل تصميم في الكون
I would say not just biological design,
لا أود ان أقول كل تصميم حيوي
but all of the design that we think of as human design.
بل كل تصميم يمكن أن نفكر فيه كجنس بشري
It's all just the same thing happening.
كل مافي الأمر أنه نفس الشيء يحدث
What did Darwin say?
ماذا قال داروين؟
I know you know the idea, natural selection,
أعلم أنكم على علم بالفكرة، الإصطفاء الطبيعي،
but let me just paraphrase "The Origin of Species," 1859,
دعوني أعيد الصياغة "أصل الأنواع،" 1859،
in a few sentences.
في بضع جمل
What Darwin said was something like this:
ماقال داروين كان شيئاَ من هذا القبيل --
if you have creatures that vary, and that can't be doubted --
إذا كان لديك كائنات مختلفة، ولايمكن أن يشكك فيها --
I've been to the Galapagos, and I've measured the size of the beaks
لقد كنت في جزر غالاباغوس ولقد قياس حجم مناقير
and the size of the turtle shells and so on, and so on.
وحجم صدفات السلاحف وهلم جرا
And 100 pages later.
و بعد 100 صفحة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And if there is a struggle for life,
وإذا كان هناك صراع من أجل الحياة
such that nearly all of these creatures die --
يحتم على جميع المخلوقات ان تموت باستثناء أحدها
and this can't be doubted, I've read Malthus
وهذا لا يمكن أن يشكك فيه، لقد قرأت مالتوس
and I've calculated how long it would take for elephants
ولقد حسبت أنني كم من الوقت سيستغرق الفيله
to cover the whole world if they bred unrestricted, and so on and so on.
لتغطية العالم بأسرة اذا تكاثرت بدون عوائق ، وهلم جرا
And another 100 pages later.
وبعد 100 صفحة
And if the very few that survive pass onto their offspring
وإذا كان القليل جدا تمكنوا من البقاء على قيد الحياة مرروا الى ذرياتهم
whatever it was that helped them survive,
أياً كان الذي ساعدهم للبقاء على قيد الحياة
then those offspring must be better adapted
إذن يجب أن تكون الذرية متكيفه بشكل أفضل
to the circumstances in which all this happened
إلى الظروف التي حدث كل هذا فيها
than their parents were.
أكثر من الآباء أنفسهم
You see the idea?
هل تلاحظون الفكرة
If, if, if, then.
أذا، اذا، أذا، إذن
He had no concept of the idea of an algorithm,
لم يكن لديه أدنى فكرة عن الخوارزمية
but that's what he described in that book,
لكن هذا ماشرحه في ذلك الكتاب
and this is what we now know as the evolutionary algorithm.
وهذا مانعرفه بالخوارزمية التطورية
The principle is you just need those three things --
المبدأ انك تحتاج الى هذه الثلاث أشياء
variation, selection and heredity.
التلون والإختيار والوراثة
And as Dan Dennett puts it, if you have those,
وكما وضعها دان دينيت، أذا كان لديك هذه
then you must get evolution.
يجب أن يكون لديك تطور
Or design out of chaos, without the aid of mind.
أو تصميم خارج من الفوضى من دون معونة من العقل
There's one word I love on that slide.
كلمة واحدة أحببتها في هذه الشريحة
What do you think my favorite word is?
ماذا تتوقعون كلمتي المفضلة؟
Audience: Chaos.
الجمهور: الفوضى
SB: Chaos? No. What? Mind? No.
سوزان بلاكمور: كلا ماذا العقل، كلا
Audience: Without.
الجمهور: بدون
SB: No, not without.
سوزان بلاكمور: كلا، ليست بدون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You try them all in order: Mmm...?
لقد حاولتم بالترتيب
Audience: Must.
الجمهور: يجب
SB: Must, at must. Must, must.
يجب، يجب على، يجب، يجب
This is what makes it so amazing.
هذا مايجعلها رائعة جداً
You don't need a designer,
لا تحتاج إلى مصمم
or a plan, or foresight, or anything else.
ولا خريطة أو رؤية ولا شيء آخر
If there's something that is copied with variation
أذا كان هناك شيء نسخ مع تغيير
and it's selected, then you must get design appearing out of nowhere.
وتم أختياره، يجب أن تحصل على تصميم يظهر من العدم
You can't stop it.
ولايمكنك إيقافه
Must is my favorite word there.
يجب هي كلمتي المفضلة هناك
Now, what's this to do with memes?
الآن، ماعلاقة هذا بالميم
Well, the principle here applies to anything
حسناً، المبدأ هنا ينطيق على كل شيء
that is copied with variation and selection.
أن يتم النسخ مع الاختلاف والاختيار
We're so used to thinking in terms of biology,
نحن معتادون على التفكير في مصطلحات علم الأحياء
we think about genes this way.
نحن نفكر في الجينات بهذه الطريقة
Darwin didn't, of course; he didn't know about genes.
داروين لم يفكر كذلك، لم يعلم ان الجينات
He talked mostly about animals and plants,
تكلم بكثرة عن الحيوانات والنباتات
but also about languages evolving and becoming extinct.
ولكن أيضا حول اللغات، تتطور وتصبح منقرضة
But the principle of Universal Darwinism
لكن مبدأ الداروينية العالمية
is that any information that is varied and selected
هل تلك المعلومات المتغيرة والمختاره
will produce design.
ستنتج تصيمياً
And this is what Richard Dawkins was on about
وهذا ماكان ريتشارد داوكنز يتحدث عنه
in his 1976 bestseller, "The Selfish Gene."
في أكثر كتبه مبيعاً عام 1976 "الجينات الأنانية"
The information that is copied, he called the replicator.
المعلومات التي نسخت .. سماها المكرر
It selfishly copies.
هي نسخ أنانية
Not meaning it kind of sits around inside cells going, "I want to get copied."
لا يقصد بأنها نوع من المجموعات حول وداخل الخلايا "أريد أن أنسخ"
But that it will get copied if it can,
ولكن من شأنها أن الحصول على نسخ أنه إذا كان ممكناً
regardless of the consequences.
بغض النظر عن النتائج
It doesn't care about the consequences because it can't,
ولا يهتم بالنتائج لأنه لا يستطيع
because it's just information being copied.
لأنها مجرد معلومات منسوخة
And he wanted to get away
وهو يريد أن يفلت
from everybody thinking all the time about genes,
من أي أحد يفكر طول الوقت عن الجينات
and so he said, "Is there another replicator out there on the planet?"
وفقال : "هل هناك مكرر (معيد تخليق) آخر على هذا الكوكب؟"
Ah, yes, there is.
أه، نعم، هناك
Look around you -- here will do, in this room.
أنظروا حولكم، هنا، في هذه الغرفة
All around us, still clumsily drifting about
حولنا، يظل ينزلق بشكل أخرق
in its primeval soup of culture, is another replicator.
في خليطه الثقافي البدائي، هو معيد تخليق
Information that we copy from person to person, by imitation,
المعلومات التي ننسخها من شخص لآخر بالمحاكاة
by language, by talking, by telling stories,
باللغة، بالكلام، بإخبار القصص
by wearing clothes, by doing things.
بإرتداء الملابس، بفعل الأشياء
This is information copied with variation and selection.
هذه المعلومات تنسخ بالتغيير والاختيار
This is design process going on.
هكذا تجري عملية التصميم
He wanted a name for the new replicator.
أراد أسماً جديداً لمعيد تخليق جديد
So, he took the Greek word "mimeme," which means that which is imitated.
أخذ الكلمة الاغريقية mimeme والتي تعني الشيئ المحاكى
Remember that, that's the core definition:
تذكر، هذا التعريف الأساسي
that which is imitated.
هذا هو محاكاتها
And abbreviated it to meme, just because it sounds good
واختصرها الى ميم (meme) فقط لتكون سهلة النطق
and made a good meme, an effective spreading meme.
وجعل الميم الجيد هو ميم سريع الانتشار
So that's how the idea came about.
أذن كيف خرجت الفكرة
It's important to stick with that definition.
مهم جدا الإلتزام بهذا التعريف
The whole science of memetics is much maligned,
كل علم الميم مطعون فيه
much misunderstood, much feared.
غير مفهوم، وعلم يجعلنا نتخوف منه
But a lot of these problems can be avoided
لكن الكثير من هذه المشاكل يمكن تجنبها
by remembering the definition.
بتذكر التعريف
A meme is not equivalent to an idea.
الميم لسيت مساوية للفكرة
It's not an idea. It's not equivalent to anything else, really.
ليست فكرة ليست مساوية لأي شيء آخر
Stick with the definition.
إلتزم بالتعريف
It's that which is imitated,
هي الشيء المحاكى
or information which is copied from person to person.
او المعلومة المنسوخة من شخص لشخص
So, let's see some memes.
أذن، دعونا نرى بعض الميم
Well, you sir, you've got those glasses hung around your neck
حسنا ، أنت يا سيدي، كنت قد حصلت على تلك النظارات معلقة حول عنقك
in that particularly fetching way.
بهذه الطريقة الجذابة
I wonder whether you invented that idea for yourself,
أتسائل ان كنت إبتكرت الفكرة بنفسك
or copied it from someone else?
أو نسخت شخصا ما
If you copied it from someone else, it's a meme.
أذا كنت نسخت شخصا ما، فهي ميم
And what about, oh, I can't see any interesting memes here.
وماذا عن...، أوه، لا أستطيع أن أرى أي ميم مثيرة للإهتمام هنا
All right everyone, who's got some interesting memes for me?
حسنا، من عنده ميم تثير انتباهي
Oh, well, your earrings,
أوه حسنا، أقراطك
I don't suppose you invented the idea of earrings.
أنا لا أفترض انك أبتكرت فكرة الأقراط
You probably went out and bought them.
على الارجح أنك ابتعتيها
There are plenty more in the shops.
هناك الكثير منها في الأسواق
That's something that's passed on from person to person.
هذا شيء إنتقل من شخص لآخر
All the stories that we're telling -- well, of course,
كل القصص التي نخبرها، بالطبع
TED is a great meme-fest, masses of memes.
تيد هو مكان لنشر الميم، الكثير من الميم
The way to think about memes, though,
الطريق الى التفكير في الميمات يرغمنا،
is to think, why do they spread?
أن نفكر، لماذا تنتشر
They're selfish information, they will get copied, if they can.
هي معلومات انانية، سيتم نسخها أن استطاعوا
But some of them will be copied because they're good,
لكن بعضها يتم نسخها لأنها جيدة
or true, or useful, or beautiful.
أو حقيقية، أو قابلة للاستخدام، أو جميلة
Some of them will be copied even though they're not.
بعضها سيتم نسخها على الرغم انها لا تنسخ
Some, it's quite hard to tell why.
البعض، من الصعب الإخبار لماذا
There's one particular curious meme which I rather enjoy.
هناك ميم غريب استمتع به في الواقع
And I'm glad to say, as I expected, I found it when I came here,
وسعيدة لاقول، أني توقعت أني أجده عندما آتي هنا
and I'm sure all of you found it, too.
ومتأكده أنكم كلكم وجدتوه ايضاً
You go to your nice, posh, international hotel somewhere,
إذهب إلى فندقك العالمي الفاخر في مكان ما
and you come in and you put down your clothes
وتعال وضع ملابسك
and you go to the bathroom, and what do you see?
واذهب الى الحمام، وماذا سترى؟
Audience: Bathroom soap.
الجمهور: صابون الحمام
SB: Pardon?
سوزان بلاكمور: عفواً
Audience: Soap.
الجمهور: صابون
SB: Soap, yeah. What else do you see?
سوزان بلاكمور: صابون، ماذا أيضاً
Audience: (Inaudible)
الجمهور: (غيرمسموع)
SB: Mmm mmm.
سوزان بلاكمور: امممم اممم
Audience: Sink, toilet!
الجمهور: حوض، مرحاض
SB: Sink, toilet, yes, these are all memes, they're all memes,
سوزان بلاكمور: حوض، مرحاض، نعم، هذه كلها ميم. كلها ميم
but they're sort of useful ones, and then there's this one.
لكنها نوع قابل للاستخدام، وهناك هذه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What is this one doing?
ماذا يفعل هذا
This has spread all over the world.
انتشر في انحاء العالم
It's not surprising that you all found it
من غير المفاجئ أن تجدوه كلكم
when you arrived in your bathrooms here.
عندما دخلتم حمامكم هنا
But I took this photograph in a toilet at the back of a tent
لكنني أخذت هذه الصورة في حمام خلف خيمة
in the eco-camp in the jungle in Assam.
في مخيم صديق للبيئة في أدغال أسام
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Who folded that thing up there, and why?
من لف هذا الشي؟ ولماذا؟
Some people get carried away.
بعض الناس ينجرفون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Other people are just lazy and make mistakes.
آخرون كسالى ويرتكبون اخطاء
Some hotels exploit the opportunity to put even more memes
بعض الفنادق تستغل الفرصة وتضع ميم أكثر
with a little sticker.
بواسطة ستيكر صغير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What is this all about?
لم كل هذا؟
I suppose it's there to tell you that somebody's
أفترض أنها هنا لتخبر بأن شخصاً
cleaned the place, and it's all lovely.
نظف المكان، وانه رائع
And you know, actually, all it tells you is that another person
وكما تعلمون، في الحقيقة هو يخبرك انه هناك شخص ما
has potentially spread germs from place to place.
نشر الجراثيم في كل مكان بشكل محتمل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, think of it this way.
أذن لنفكر بهذه الطريقة
Imagine a world full of brains
تخيل عالم مليئ بالعقول
and far more memes than can possibly find homes.
ويمكن للميم البحث عن منازل
The memes are all trying to get copied --
والميم كلها تحاول أن تنسخ
trying, in inverted commas -- i.e.,
تحاول، في الفاصلة المقلوبة كمثال
that's the shorthand for, if they can get copied, they will.
هو أختصال لـ ، أذا استطاعت أن تنسخ فستفعل
They're using you and me as their propagating, copying machinery,
يستخدموني انا وأنتم كآلات نسخ ونشر
and we are the meme machines.
ونحن آلات الميم
Now, why is this important?
والأن، لماذا هذا مهم؟
Why is this useful, or what does it tell us?
لم هو مفيد، او ماذا يمكن أن يخبرنا؟
It gives us a completely new view of human origins
انه بعطينا رؤية جديدة تماماً لأصل الإنسان
and what it means to be human,
وماذا يعني أن تكون انساناً
all conventional theories of cultural evolution,
كل النظريات التقليدية للتطور الثقافي
of the origin of humans,
لأصل البشر
and what makes us so different from other species.
وماذا يجعلنا مختلفين عن الأنواع الاخرى
All other theories explaining the big brain, and language, and tool use
كل النظريات الأخرى تشرح الدماغ الكبير واللغة واستخدام أداة
and all these things that make us unique,
وكل هذه الأشياء تجعلنا مختلفين
are based upon genes.
تقوم على الجينات
Language must have been useful for the genes.
اللغات يجب أن تكون قابلة للإستخدام للجينات
Tool use must have enhanced our survival, mating and so on.
استخدام الاداة يجب ان يعزز بقائنا، التزاوج وهلم جرا
It always comes back, as Richard Dawkins complained
وهو يعود الى الوراء كما يقول ريتشارد داوكنز
all that long time ago, it always comes back to genes.
في الماضي، كان يعود الى الجينات
The point of memetics is to say, "Oh no, it doesn't."
في النقطة التي يقول علم الميم "أوه أنه لايفعل"
There are two replicators now on this planet.
هنالك الآن نوعان من معيدي التخليق في هذا الكوكب
From the moment that our ancestors,
منذ تلك الحظة التي بدأ أجدادنا -
perhaps two and a half million years ago or so,
ربما قرابة مليونان و نصف مليون سنة مضت
began imitating, there was a new copying process.
بدأوا التقليد . كان هنالك نوع جديد من عمليات النسخ.
Copying with variation and selection.
النسخ باختلاف و انتقائية.
A new replicator was let loose, and it could never be --
معيد تخليق جديد قد اطلق , و لم يكن
right from the start -- it could never be
من البداية , لم يكن ..
that human beings who let loose this new creature,
الكائن البشري ليطلق هذا المخلوق الجديد.
could just copy the useful, beautiful, true things,
كان بالإمكان نسخ الأشياء المفيدة و الجميلة , الأشياء الحقيقية,
and not copy the other things.
و ليس نسخ الأشياء الأخرى.
While their brains were having an advantage from being able to copy --
عندما كانت عقولهم تستفيد من كونها قادرة على نسخ--
lighting fires, keeping fires going, new techniques of hunting,
النيران الصاعقة ,ابقائهم للنار مشتعلة , تقنيات الصيد الجديدة,
these kinds of things --
هذا النوع من الأشياء--
inevitably they were also copying putting feathers in their hair,
حتما كانوا ينسخون وضع الريش على شعورهم
or wearing strange clothes, or painting their faces,
أو لبس الملابس الغريبة , أو الرسم على وجوههم,
or whatever.
أو أياً كان.
So, you get an arms race between the genes
إذاً , سوف تحصل على سباق بين الجينات
which are trying to get the humans to have small economical brains
كلها تحاول أن تجعل البشر يحصلون على عقول صغيرة, و اقتصادية
and not waste their time copying all this stuff,
و ليس تضييع أوقاتهم في نسخ كل هذه الأشياء,
and the memes themselves, like the sounds that people made and copied --
و الميمات بنفسها , مثل الصوت الذي يصنعه البشر , و ينسخوه
in other words, what turned out to be language --
بعبارة أخرى , الذي اتضح أن اللغة
competing to get the brains to get bigger and bigger.
تتنافس لجعل العقول أكبر , و أكبر .
So, the big brain, on this theory, is driven by the memes.
لذلك , العقل الكبير في هذه النظرية يقاد من قبل الميمات.
This is why, in "The Meme Machine," I called it memetic drive.
لهذا السبب في " آلة الميمات" ,سميتها مدفوعة الميمية
As the memes evolve, as they inevitably must,
كلما تطورت الميمات , كما يجب عليها طبعاَ
they drive a bigger brain that is better at copying the memes
اصبحت قادرة على قيادة عقول أكبر و أفضل في نسخ الميمات
that are doing the driving.
التي تقوم بالتحكم.
This is why we've ended up with such peculiar brains,
و هذا هو السبب في حصولنا على عقلول مميزة
that we like religion, and music, and art.
تحب الدين , و الموسيقى , و الفن.
Language is a parasite that we've adapted to,
اللغة هي طفيلي اعتدنا عليه
not something that was there originally for our genes,
و ليس شيئا كان هنالك اصلا من أجل جيناتنا
on this view.
بوجهة النظر هذه.
And like most parasites, it can begin dangerous,
و كما كل الطفيليات , قد تكون خطرة
but then it coevolves and adapts,
و لكن بعد ذلك, قد تتطور بالتعوان معنا
and we end up with a symbiotic relationship
و ينتهي بنا الحال معاً في علاقة تكافلية
with this new parasite.
مع هذه الطفيليات الجديدة .
And so, from our perspective,
و كذلك من وجهة نظرنا
we don't realize that that's how it began.
نحن لا ندرك أنها هكذا بدأت
So, this is a view of what humans are.
لذلك هذه مثال على حقيقة البشر.
All other species on this planet are gene machines only,
كل الكائنات الأخرى على هذا الكوكب آلات, آلات جينية فقط,
they don't imitate at all well, hardly at all.
لا تحاكي قطعاً.
We alone are gene machines and meme machines as well.
نحن وحدنا آلات جينية و آلات ميمية ايضاً
The memes took a gene machine and turned it into a meme machine.
الميمات اخذت آلة جينية و حولتها الى آلة جينية
But that's not all.
و لكن ذلك ليس كل الحكاية
We have a new kind of memes now.
نحن نملك الآن نوعا جديداً من الميمات
I've been wondering for a long time,
كنت اتسائل لوقت طويل
since I've been thinking about memes a lot,
بما انني افكر في الميمات كثيراً
is there a difference between the memes that we copy --
هل هنالك فرق بين الميمات التي ننسخها
the words we speak to each other,
و بين الكلمات التي نقولها لبعضنا العبض.
the gestures we copy, the human things --
الفتات الذي ننسخ,الأشياء البشرية--
and all these technological things around us?
و كل الأشياء التقنية حولنا؟
I have always, until now, called them all memes,
كنت دوماً , إلى الآن أدعوها كلها ميمات
but I do honestly think now
و لكنني بصدق اعتقد الآن
we need a new word for technological memes.
اننا نحتاج كلمة جديدة للتقنيات الميمية
Let's call them techno-memes or temes.
فلنسمها التكنو-ميمات , او التيمات.
Because the processes are getting different.
لان العمليات اصبحت مختلفة
We began, perhaps 5,000 years ago, with writing.
بدأنا , قبل قرابة 5000 سنة بالكتابة
We put the storage of memes out there on a clay tablet,
وضعنا حافظات الميمات هنالك في الخارج على ألواح طينية
but in order to get true temes and true teme machines,
ولكن للحصول تيمات حقيقية و آلات تيمية حقيقية
you need to get the variation, the selection and the copying,
يجب عليك أن تجعل التفرقة و الإنتقاية و النسخ
all done outside of humans.
كلها تحصل خارج البشر
And we're getting there.
و نحن نقترب من ذلك.
We're at this extraordinary point where we're nearly there,
نحن هنا في مرحلة استثنائية ,حيث أننا على وشك أن نكون هناك
that there are machines like that.
حيث يوجد آلات مشابههة.
And indeed, in the short time I've already been at TED,
و بالفعل ,في الوقت القصير الذي كنت فيه في تيد TED
I see we're even closer than I thought we were before.
أرى أننا اقرب مما كنت اعتقد
So actually, now the temes are forcing our brains
لذلك بالفعل , التيمات الآن تجبر عقولنا
to become more like teme machines.
لكي تصبح كالآلات التيمية
Our children are growing up very quickly learning to read,
أطفالنا ينمون بسرعة و يتعمون القراءة بسرعة
learning to use machinery.
و يتعلمون استخدام الآت.
We're going to have all kinds of implants,
سوف نحصل على كل أنواع المزروعات.
drugs that force us to stay awake all the time.
أدوية تجبرنا على البقاء مستيقظين كل الوقت.
We'll think we're choosing these things,
سوف نعتقد أننا نختار هذه الأشياء بمحض ارادتنا
but the temes are making us do it.
و لكن في الحقيقة , التيمات هي ما يجبرنا على فعل هذه الأشياء
So, we're at this cusp now
إذاً , نحن على وشك
of having a third replicator on our planet.
الحصول على معيد تخليق ثالث في كوكبنا
Now, what about what else is going on out there in the universe?
الآن , ماذا عن باقي الأشياء التي تحصل في كوكبنا ؟
Is there anyone else out there?
هل هنالك أحد ما خارج هذا الكوكب؟
People have been asking this question for a long time.
الناس تسأل هذا السؤال منذ زمن بعيد
We've been asking it here at TED already.
نحن سألنا هذا السؤال ايضا في تيد TED
In 1961, Frank Drake made his famous equation,
في عام 1961 فرانك درايك وضع معادلته الشهيرة
but I think he concentrated on the wrong things.
لكنني اعتقد انه ركز على الأشياء الخطأ
It's been very productive, that equation.
لقد كانت فاعلة جداً , تلك المعادلة,
He wanted to estimate N,
أراد أن يحدد قيمة تقريبية لـ ع
the number of communicative civilizations out there in our galaxy,
العدد التقريبي للحضارات التي قد نتواصل معها خارج المجرة
and he included in there the rate of star formation,
و تضمن في معادلته معدل تكون النجوم
the rate of planets, but crucially, intelligence.
و معدل الكواكب , و بشكل حاسم , الذكاء.
I think that's the wrong way to think about it.
أعتقد انها طريقة خاطئة للنظر في الموضوع
Intelligence appears all over the place, in all kinds of guises.
الذكاء يظهر في كل أنحاء المكان , في كل أنواع الكائنات
Human intelligence is only one kind of a thing.
ذكاء البشر هو نوع واحد فقط.
But what's really important is the replicators you have
و لكن ما يهم حقاً هو معيد التخليق الذي تملكه الآن
and the levels of replicators, one feeding on the one before.
و مستواه بين اشباهه ’ واحد يتغذى على ما قبله
So, I would suggest that we don't think intelligence,
لذلك أنا اقترح أن نفكر في الذكاء ,
we think replicators.
بل نفكر في معيدي التخليق
And on that basis, I've suggested a different kind of equation.
و على هذه الاساس , أنا اقترح معادلة من نوع جديد
A very simple equation.
معادلة بسيطة جداً
N, the same thing,
على , الشيء نفسه
the number of communicative civilizations out there
العدد التقريبي للحضارات التي قد نتواصل معها خارج المجرة
[that] we might expect in our galaxy.
الذي قد نتوقعه داخل مجرتنا
Just start with the number of planets there are in our galaxy.
فقط نبدأ بعدد الكواكب في مجرتنا
The fraction of those which get a first replicator.
جزء منها يحصلون على المُكرِر الأول
The fraction of those that get the second replicator.
جزء منها يحصلون على المُكرِر الثاني
The fraction of those that get the third replicator.
جزء منها يحصلون على المُكرر الثالث
Because it's only the third replicator that's going to reach out --
ولأنه فقط المُكرر الثالث الذي سوف يصل إلى
sending information, sending probes, getting out there,
إرسال المعلومات والتحقيقات، والخروج من هناك
and communicating with anywhere else.
والتواصل مع أي مكان آخر
OK, so if we take that equation,
حسناً. إذا أخذنا تلك المعادلة
why haven't we heard from anybody out there?
لماذا لم نسمع أي أحد من تلك الجهة ؟
Because every step is dangerous.
لأن كل خطوة خطيرة
Getting a new replicator is dangerous.
الحصول على مُكرِر جديد أمر خطير
You can pull through, we have pulled through,
من الممكن أن نسحب، يجب أن نسحب
but it's dangerous.
ولكن الأمر خطير.
Take the first step, as soon as life appeared on this earth.
اتخذ الخطوة الأولى، حالما تظهر الحياة في الأرض
We may take the Gaian view.
نستطيع أن نأخذ نظرة جايان
I loved Peter Ward's talk yesterday -- it's not Gaian all the time.
أنا أعجبتي كلمات بيتر بالأمس، لم تكن جايانية طول الوقت
Actually, life forms produce things that kill themselves.
في الواقع، أشكال الحياة تنتج أشياء تقتل نفسها..
Well, we did pull through on this planet.
حسنا، لقد تم سحبنا على هذا الكوكب
But then, a long time later, billions of years later,
ولكن، وبعد زمن طويل يقدر بملايين السنين
we got the second replicator, the memes.
حصلنا على المُكرِر الثاني، الميمات
That was dangerous, all right.
كان الأمر خطيرا، أليس كذلك ؟
Think of the big brain.
فكر بالدماغ الكبير
How many mothers do we have here?
كم عدد الأمهات الحاضرات هنا ؟
You know all about big brains.
تعرفون كل شيء عن الأدمغة الكبيرة..
They are dangerous to give birth to,
إنها خطيرة أثناء الولادة..
are agonizing to give birth to.
ومؤلمة كذلك
(Laughter)
ضحك
My cat gave birth to four kittens, purring all the time.
قطتي ولدت أربع قطط.. يخرخرون طول الوقت
Ah, mm -- slightly different.
آه... ، يختلفون قليلا
(Laughter)
ضحك
But not only is it painful, it kills lots of babies,
ولكنها ليست فقط مؤلمة .. بل تقتل الكثير من الأطفال
it kills lots of mothers,
وتقتل الكثير من الأمهات
and it's very expensive to produce.
إنها مكلفة جدا في عملية إنتاجها
The genes are forced into producing all this myelin,
الجينات مجبرة على أن تنتج كل هذا المايلن
all the fat to myelinate the brain.
وكل الدهون التي تعزل الدماغ
Do you know, sitting here,
هل تعلم ، أنك بجلوسك هنا
your brain is using about 20 percent of your body's energy output
فدماغك يستخدم حوالي عشرين بالمئة من طاقة جسدك المُنتجة
for two percent of your body weight?
لاثنين بالمئة من وزن جسدك.
It's a really expensive organ to run.
إنها عضويات مكلفة حقاً في عملها
Why? Because it's producing the memes.
لماذا؟ لأنها تنتج الميمات.
Now, it could have killed us off. It could have killed us off,
الآن.. يمكن أن تكون قتلتنا..
and maybe it nearly did, but you see, we don't know.
ويمكن أن تكون على وشك ذك.. ولكننا، لا نعلم.
But maybe it nearly did.
ولكن يمكن أن تكون فعلت ذلك تقريبا..
Has it been tried before?
هل حاولت ذلك من قبل ؟
What about all those other species?
وماذا عن كل هذه الأنواع الأخرى ؟
Louise Leakey talked yesterday
لويس ليكي تحدث بالأمس
about how we're the only one in this branch left.
عن كيف أننا الوحيدين في هذا الفرع الأيسر
What happened to the others?
ماذا حل بالآخرين ؟
Could it be that this experiment in imitation,
هل يمكن أن تكون هذه التجربة في المحاكاة
this experiment in a second replicator,
هذه التجربة في المُكرِر الثاني
is dangerous enough to kill people off?
خطيرة بما يكفي لتقتل الناس ؟
Well, we did pull through, and we adapted.
حسنا، لقد اجتزنا وتوائمنا
But now, we're hitting, as I've just described,
ولكن الآن.. فنحن نقترب - كما أوضحت لكم
we're hitting the third replicator point.
نقترب من المُكرِر الثالث
And this is even more dangerous --
وهذا بالفعل أكثر خطراً
well, it's dangerous again.
هذا خطير..
Why? Because the temes are selfish replicators
لماذا ؟ لأن التيمات مكررات أنانية
and they don't care about us, or our planet, or anything else.
ولا يهتمون بنا، ولا بكوكبنا، ولا بأي شيء آخر..
They're just information, why would they?
كل هذه معلومات فحسب! فلم يفعلون ذلك؟
They are using us to suck up the planet's resources
هم يستخدموننا ليمتصوا موارد الكوكب
to produce more computers,
ليصنعوا حاسبات أكثر
and more of all these amazing things we're hearing about here at TED.
واكثر من هذه الأشياء المدهشة التي نسمعها في تيد TED
Don't think, "Oh, we created the Internet for our own benefit."
لا تعتقد "أوه، لقد صنعنا الانترنت لفائدتنا"
That's how it seems to us.
هذا مايبدوا لنا
Think, temes spreading because they must.
فكر التيمات تنتشر لأنه عليها الإنتشار
We are the old machines.
نحن الآلات القديمة
Now, are we going to pull through?
الان هل سيتم سحبنا؟
What's going to happen?
ماذا سيحدث
What does it mean to pull through?
ماذا يعني انه يتم سحبنا
Well, there are kind of two ways of pulling through.
حسنا، هناك طريقتين لسحبنا
One that is obviously happening all around us now,
أحدها يحدث بوضوح حولنا الآن
is that the temes turn us into teme machines,
هل التيمات تحولنا الى مكائن لها
with these implants, with the drugs,
مع غرسات، وعقارات
with us merging with the technology.
مع الأندماج بالتفنية
And why would they do that?
ولماذا يفعلون ذلك
Because we are self-replicating.
لأنهم معادو التخليق ذاتياً
We have babies.
لدينا أطفال
We make new ones, and so it's convenient to piggyback on us,
نعمل من جديد ونجعلها مناسبة للحمل على الظهر
because we're not yet at the stage on this planet
لأننا لسنا بعد في مرحلة على الكوكب
where the other option is viable.
حيث الخيار الآخر موجود
Although it's closer, I heard this morning,
على الرغم أنه قريب، سمعت هذا الصباح
it's closer than I thought it was.
أنه أقرب مما توقعت
Where the teme machines themselves will replicate themselves.
حيث التميمات ألات تعيد تخليق نفسها بنفسها
That way, it wouldn't matter if the planet's climate
بهذا الطريقة، لا يهم أذا المناخ على الكوكب
was utterly destabilized,
كان غير مستقر تماماً
and it was no longer possible for humans to live here.
وأصبح من غير الممكن للبشر العيش
Because those teme machines, they wouldn't need --
لأن آلات التيمات لن تحتاج
they're not squishy, wet, oxygen-breathing,
هم ليسو اسفنجيين، ولا رطبين، ولا يتنفسون الأكسيجين
warmth-requiring creatures.
مخلوقات محتاجة للدفئ
They could carry on without us.
ويمكن أن يكملوا بدوننا
So, those are the two possibilities.
أّذن هناك إحتمالان
The second, I don't think we're that close.
الثاني، لا أعتقد اننا بهذا القرب
It's coming, but we're not there yet.
سيأتي، لكننا لسنا هناك بعد
The first, it's coming too.
الأول، أنه آتي أيضاً
But the damage that is already being done
لكن الضرر يحدث بالفعل
to the planet is showing us how dangerous the third point is,
للكوكب يرينا خطورة النقطة الثالثة
that third danger point, getting a third replicator.
نفطة الخطورة الثالثة تكون معيد تخليق ثالث
And will we get through this third danger point,
وهل نتجاوز نقطة الخطر الثالثة
like we got through the second and like we got through the first?
كما تجازونا الثانية والأولى
Maybe we will, maybe we won't.
من الممكن ومن الممكن أن لا نفعل
I have no idea.
ليس لدي أي فكرة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: That was an incredible talk.
كريس أنديرسون: لقد كان كلاما مدهشاَ
SB: Thank you. I scared myself.
سوزان بلاكمور: شكرا، لقد أخفت نفسي
CA: (Laughter)
كريس أنديرسون: (ضحك)